<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the funerals of that worthy personage George Purefoy the elder of Wadley in Berks, esq., who was buried by his ancestors at Drayton in Leicestershire, April 21, 1661 by Jo. Hinckley.</title>
            <author>Hinckley, John, 1617?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11833467</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11833467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 497:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the funerals of that worthy personage George Purefoy the elder of Wadley in Berks, esq., who was buried by his ancestors at Drayton in Leicestershire, April 21, 1661 by Jo. Hinckley.</title>
                  <author>Hinckley, John, 1617?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Purefoy, George, d. 1661.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D AT THE FUNERALS Of that Worthy Perſonage <hi>GEORGE P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>REFOY</hi> The Elder of <hi>Wadley</hi> in <hi>Berks,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Who was buried by his Anceſtors at <hi>Dray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire, April</hi> 21. 1661.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jo. Hinckley.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quid in obitu dolendum? cum ad vitam miſeria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum expertem proficiſcitur; ubi nulli plagarum dolores: mortui potius ſuperſtites miſereantur, ut carcere incluſos.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Greg. Nyſſ. Ser. de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis, p. 586.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> in S. <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church yard in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49740:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49740:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 25.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then <hi>Abraham</hi> gave up the Ghoſt, and died in a good old age, an old man, and full of years, and was gathered to his people.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is obſerv'd of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that in the Entrance of his Epiſtles, like a compleat <hi>Tertullus,</hi> or ready <hi>Orator,</hi> he did firſt <hi>Captare bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volentiam, &amp; demereri populum,</hi> that is, inſinuate himſelf into the good opinion, and liking of the people to whom he wrote: courting them (as it were) with winning terms, and appellations; as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>beloved, my Son Timothy,</hi> and the like: exſtolling their <hi>Faith, Love</hi> and <hi>Saint-ſhip:</hi> melting them too, with kind and hearty ſalutations, <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> alſo, that learned Evangeliſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>moſt excellent Theophilus:</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> uſhers in one of his Epiſtles, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating it to the <hi>Elect Lady;</hi> Theſe were all expert fiſhers of men, and ſo well knew how to bait their hooks that they might catch the Soules of men. That doctrine is ſwallowed moſt ſweetly, and that Sermon digeſted moſt ſoundly, which is wrapped up in a ſugard, and ſavory conceit of the Preachers worth, learning, affectionate tenderneſſe and integrity. Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation here is moſt operative: This ſubdues the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49740:3"/>hearts of men unto the obedience of the word, as once the very fame of <hi>Alexander</hi> did not a little conduce to the conquering of puiſſant Armies.</p>
            <p>Fain would I (at this preſent, at this Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Auditory) obſerve the method, and walk in the footſteps of ſo grand Exemplar's; I mean, I would gain your <hi>Penelope,</hi> by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and conſpiracy of your own Maides: Captivate your judgements and wills to the attention, and imbracing of the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, by the innocent <hi>Lenocinium,</hi> or harmleſs trechery of your own affections.</p>
            <p>To this end, I ſhall level the Artillery of my weak Rhetorick, make my Battery and invaſion, firſt, upon you my Friends, Neighbours, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, you that like the Sons of Iſrael, have accompanied our <hi>Father Jacob, Patrum Patriae,</hi> a Father of our Country, hither to his <hi>Mamre,</hi> his <hi>Cave of Macpelah:</hi> you, that like thoſe devout men, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. have brought <hi>Stephen</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, indeed our <hi>Crown,</hi> our <hi>Glory</hi> to his burial. And now me thinks, I could gladly deſcend this Mount, and goe aſide with you into the Vally, of <hi>Baca,</hi> or to <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> to draw water; full buckets of water, at the Conduits of our eyes. I could even deal with you as <hi>Jacob</hi> did with his Son <hi>Joſeph, Gen.</hi> 46.28. <hi>Fall upon your necks,</hi> and vie tears with you, until we have made a <hi>great mourning,</hi> as once was made for the death of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> ſetting all our notes to the tune of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dadrimmon.</hi> For Alas, Sirs! what a poor deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49740:3"/>viduated, infeebled, gloomy Country ſhall we find at our return? After we have parted with ſuch a <hi>Father</hi> out of our Iſrael, ſuch a <hi>Stake</hi> out of our hedg, ſuch a <hi>Ceder</hi> out of our <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Luminary</hi> out of our Hemiſphear. But whither am I now going? It is time to break through this cloud; and to ſtop this tragical veine. My ay me at firſt, was not ſo much to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole, as to congratulate with you, and to thank you for your company, in the deads behalf; you have done the greateſt favour, that either he was capable to receive, or your ſelves to beſtow: we can but bring our friends to the grave, and there for a time we muſt leave them.</p>
            <p>You alſo the Natives, and Inhabitants of this place, let me preface and beſpeak you in a word, or two: A <hi>Stranger</hi> to <hi>Strangers;</hi> Sirs, although we injoyed the company of this worthy perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, <hi>&amp; gratias agimus, quod illum habere meru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imus;</hi> may we never be unthankful to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bernardus</hi> in Cant. Ser. 26.</note> for the ſociety of ſuch a neighbour! yet his thoughts were much upon you; and his diſcourſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently off this place, and at laſt, he bequeathed part of himſelf to you: His Body to reſt with your bodies, his <hi>Bones with your Bones.</hi> So <hi>King Edward</hi> the firſt in our own Chronicles, ſignifieth his great affection to the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> by orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his heart to be buried there, after his death. And as the place of <hi>Homer's</hi> birth was thereby made famous and illuſtrious, ſo ſhall this village receive no ſmall honour from this <hi>Heroes</hi> birth, and burial: Tell me now, Can we be but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49740:4"/>too welcome, that have brought ſuch a legacy along with us? Can we be but too welcome, that have brought the rich ſpoil of our own Countrey to adorn your Temple?</p>
            <p>But I muſt ſuperſede theſe complemental in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations: I muſt leave the Son too for a while, and come to the Father, for here are no leſſe than two funerals: The firſt of <hi>Abraham, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithful.</hi> The ſecond of this Son of <hi>Abraham;</hi> But it is fit the Father ſhould have the precedency: <hi>Then Abraham gave up the Ghoſt, and dyed in a good old age, an old man, and full of years, and was gathered to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the foregoing verſes acquaint us with <hi>Abrahams Teſtament,</hi> and therein his great care in diſpoſing and ſetling his outward eſtate, to prevent differences, and controverſies among his poſterity, leſt tedious ſuits ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd upon his Children, together with his Land, and his other ſubſtance. And this hath been the providence of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and many other Saints, <hi>to ſet their houſes in order,</hi> before they have gone to the place where all things are forgotten. The manner of his Will is alſo very obſervable, <hi>He gave all that he had unto Iſaac,</hi> v. 5. yet this cannot be any plea; much leſſe afford any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, or patronage, to ſuch cruel and injuſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (whoſe younger Children fare no better than their Hogs, as once was ſaid of <hi>Herod</hi>) who either for light cauſes diſinherit their Children, or elſe make one of them a Gentleman, and leave
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49740:4"/>other beggars, for <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the only Son of <hi>Sarah</hi> his lawful and legitimate wife, his other children were the Sons of <hi>Concubines, v.</hi> 6. Now <hi>Concubines</hi> were for the bed indeed, but not for the honour of the family, taken without eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and ſo might be put away again, neither could their Children inherit. Therefore <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.2. the Sons of <hi>Gilead</hi> told <hi>Jephtah, He ſhould not inherit in their fathers houſe, becauſe he was the Son of a ſtrange woman.</hi> To this St. <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. <hi>The Son of the bond-woman ſhall not be heir with the Son of the Free-woman;</hi> They only had ſome ſmaller gifts beſtowed upon them.<note place="margin">In <hi>Denmark</hi> the ſecond wife had no part of the mans inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but gifts out of his eſtate cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Morgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gab.</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>So Abraham gave gifts to his other Sons.</hi> v. 6. A <hi>Learned man</hi> obſerves, that the ſame cuſtome is in <hi>Denmark</hi> to this day, yet waving any further diſquiſition, or ſearch further into the context: I ſhall come at laſt to thoſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable circumſtances which are in the Text it ſelfe, concerning the death, and burial of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon dying, <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The manner of his death, <hi>He gave up the Ghoſt and dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The time when he dyed; <hi>In a good Old Age, an old Man, and full of yeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How he was diſpoſed of after death; <hi>and was gathered to his people.</hi> Theſe parts are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the text, without either ſtraining it, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuring them, with any termes of art. I muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon dying, <hi>Abraham: And Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49740:5"/>gave up the Ghoſt,</hi> Abraham <hi>a great Prince, a great Prophet, a great man in eſtate,</hi> the <hi>friend of God,</hi> the <hi>Father of the faithful:</hi> Titles enough (one would have thought) to have ſtruck a we into death it ſelf, as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>impudent,</hi> or diſreſpecter of perſons, as it is; yet notwithſtanding, all this pomp and <hi>grandeur, Abraham gave up the Ghoſt, and dyed.</hi> No prerogative whatſoever will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt us from death, though we be the favorites of Heaven, the Potentates of the Earth, the darlings of the people; yet our breath is ſtill in our Noſtrils, we are as much obnoxious, &amp; expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the arrowes of death, as the pooreſt <hi>Muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room,</hi> or <hi>Shrub,</hi> the meaneſt peaſant that crawls on the ſurface of the Earth. The Pſalmiſt puts it to a negative queſtion, <hi>What man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death? Shall he deliver his Soul from the hand of the Grave?</hi> Pſa. 89.48. The word is not <hi>Adam,</hi> or <hi>Enos;</hi> but <hi>Geber.</hi> What rich, what mighty, what great Man is there that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death? And that we might not paſſe from that text without ſerious conſidering the purport of it, he arreſts our ſpirits with that ſignal and emphatical note, <hi>Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, or laſt, we muſt all travel this common road, which hath been beaten by the feet of all our forefathers; And indeed, this is alſo a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon &amp; beaten truth, that I am upon; none doubt of it in their underſtandings, &amp; retired thoughts: yet becauſe there is a great difference betwixt a ſimple notional, and ſpeculative knowledge of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49740:5"/>a truth, ſwimming upon the underſtanding, and a practical ſanctified experimental &amp; reduplicative knowledge, when we know the truth, <hi>as we ought to knowing,</hi> by influencing our wills, tempering our affections, and ſteering all the courſes and paſſages of the outward man, which is called by the Apoſtle, <hi>a knowledge according to godlineſs,</hi> or <hi>Knowing of the truth, as it is in Jeſus.</hi> I fear we do not know this truth, (in this ſenſe) as common as it is, elſe what means the <hi>bleating of the Sheep, and the lowing of the Oxon in our eares?</hi> what is the reaſon that ſo many live as if they ſhould never dye? ſet their hearts upon their <hi>habitations,</hi> as if their <hi>habitations</hi> ſhould endure for ever? As if they <hi>ſhould dye in their Neſts, and multiply their daies as the Sand,</hi> Job. 29.18. They are ready to ſay with <hi>David</hi> in his proſperity, <hi>that they ſhall never be moved;</hi> or with the Whore of <hi>Babylon, I ſhall ſit as Queen for ever.</hi> Had thoſe Atheiſtical wreches learned this leſſon, who <hi>put far from them the evil day,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Come, I will fetch wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant,</hi> Eſa. 56.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> well knew the difficulty of taking forth this truth, therefore about to make a Sermon of mans frailty, he begins thus, <hi>I will encline my ear to a parable, I will open my dark ſayings,</hi> Pſ. 49.4. And the Prophet being about to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, <hi>All Fleſh is graſſe, and all the goodlineſſe thereof, as the flower of the feild.</hi> He brings it in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49740:6"/>with a ſolemnity of a dialogue, betwixt a voice from Heaven, and himſelf, <hi>The voice ſaid cry; and he ſaid, what ſhall I cry?</hi> Iſa. 40.6. That ſaying was ſo dark, and our natures ſo averſe to digeſt it; that there is need of crying, and crying again.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that as it was in the daies of <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Lot;</hi> So it is in our daies, ther's eating, drinking, building, and beating, by oppreſſion, of our fellow ſervants, untill the Flood of death, like the river <hi>Kiſon, ſweep us away. Hannibal ad portas,</hi> the great Philiſtin, or laſt enemy is upon us; yet we are not drawn forth into battalia, mounted our battlements, or have our weapons fixed. The Bridegroom is coming a pace, yet our lamps were neither trim'd, nor furniſhed with oyle.</p>
            <p>Did <hi>Abraham</hi> give up the Ghoſt, though he was the friend of God? then let us not only make a good uſe of good men, whilſt we have them; by ſucking and drawing from them the hony of advice and Counſel; for there is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or knowledge in the grave; though the lips of faithful and able Miniſters (whilſt alive) may drop as the hony-comb; yet their Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres cannot edifie, or inſtruct us; <hi>the living, the living ſhall praiſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>Abraham</hi> Gods familiar, and intimate friend, gave up the Ghoſt, and dyed: ſure death is not ſo terrible, as moſt apprehend it to be, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe his deareſt ſervant ſhould not have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of it. The Apoſtle caſts ſome ſpice into the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49740:6"/>cup of affliction, and endeavours to ſweeten chaſtiſements by this argument, becauſe they fall upon the Sons and children of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.7, 8. As the grave it ſelf (methink's) is perfumed for us, in that Chriſt himſelf was pleaſed to ſleep in that Chamber.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Abraham</hi> was great in power, &amp; eſtate, yet he gave up the Ghoſt, and dyed: therefore let's not <hi>make fleſh our arm,</hi> in relying upon any of the Sons of men, though never ſo mighty. They are but as ſo many dreams, ſhadowes, or puffes of wind, <hi>ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils; for what excellency is there in him?</hi> Iſa. 2.22. <hi>Truſt not in Princes, nor in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Sons of men,</hi> Pſa. 146.3. And leſt we ſhould be left utterly deſtitute of any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to bare us up, <hi>David</hi> adds, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Happy is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God:</hi> As if all ſtaies were but as ſo many broken Reeds, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Rock of ages. <hi>Alexander</hi> (as great as he was) once the Idol of his Court was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent at laſt with a coffin: And <hi>Diogines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sarcofago contentus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. <hi>Juv.</hi>
               </note> is brought in by <hi>Lucian,</hi> as jearing the Ghoſt of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> after death, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? what, is <hi>Alexander</hi> dead, as well as <hi>Diogenes? Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> had then learned, that he was not immortal, and could ſay; Tis<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Clem. Alex. p. 61.</note> no wonder, that I am dead, ſeeing at beſt, I was but a man. <hi>Saladine</hi> alſo that great Commander, who won <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> gave order to have no other ſolemnity at his funeral, than to have a Cryer to goe before his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49740:7"/>herſe to give notice to the people, that there was <hi>Saladine</hi> the Conqueror of the Eaſt, and how, that of all his riches and glory., he carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing with him but his ſhirt. And what help can they afford to others, that have not been able to help themſelves:</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note n="2" place="margin">2. Part.</note> The manner of his death; <hi>He gave up the Ghoſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Expiravit,</hi> or as it is ſaid of Chriſt himſelf, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>breath'd out</hi> his laſt breath, to ſhew that we are but as ſo many bubbles or blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; touch, or prick us, and we are gone, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhrivel together, and as the heavens ſhal be at the laſt day, are contracted and <hi>drawn together like a Scrowl.</hi> if God blow upon us, like ſo many untimely figs, we fall and ſhatter; our ruddy cheeks become pale and wan, <hi>thou changeſt his countenance, and ſendeſt him away:</hi> Job. 14.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He gave up the Ghoſt;</hi> that is, he wilingly ſurrendred his Soul into the hands of God; So Chriſt bowed his head upon the Croſſe, as it were to ſalute and welcome death it ſelf, even as he expanded and ſtreched out his armes, to ſignifie how ready he was to imbrace penitent ſinners. Gods people hath ſome preſentments of a better Countrey; Some aſſurance of going to more glorious company; They have an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Chriſt, and <hi>ſo love his appearance,</hi> as well at the day of death, as of judgement: they have <hi>fought a good fight,</hi> and therefore are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>that Garland, that crown of Glory, which is repoſited and laid
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49740:7"/>up <hi>for them, in the bands of a faithful Creator;</hi> They have <hi>taſted that the Lord is gracious,</hi> by the reliſh of thoſe firſt fruits, thoſe bunches of Grapes, which the holy ſpies, the Miniſters of the Lord, have brought unto them from the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and therefore, with the ſpouſe <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.4. <hi>They long to goe to the vineyard it ſelf, to the beds of ſpices, to feed in the Garden, and to gather Lillies:</hi> with <hi>Simeon,</hi> they are ready to ſing, <hi>nunc dimittis, now let thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant depart in peace;</hi> or with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>to be deſolved <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>migrare revertere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scultetus.</note> to depart, <hi>and to returne unto Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is to inform us concerning the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the death of Gods ſervants, and the wicked; The one reſign up their lives, and give up their ghoſts willingly; from the other they are wreſted, and hal'd: The world ſticks ſo cloſe to them, that they know not how to ſhake it off, they are clogged, <hi>and preſſed down with ſo many weights</hi> they are pinion'd with ſo many ſins, <hi>that do eaſily beſet them,</hi> that they cannot mount upwards: Their darling ſins, and boſome corruptions come about them, as once St. <hi>Anstins</hi> luſt did cling about him: <hi>Non eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tecum in aeternum?</hi> What, ſhall we never be drunk, prophane, and unchaſt any more? Their Souls are fetcht from them violently, as it were with a Purſevant, <hi>this night ſhall thy Soul be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from thee,</hi> Luke 12.20. like ruſty ſwords they are hardly drawn out of the Sheathes of their bodies; to this <hi>Daniel</hi> alludes, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7.15. <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49740:8"/>ſpirit was grieved within me:</hi> the <hi>Chaldee</hi> reads it, my ſpirit was grieved within my Sheath, and good reaſon they have to hang back, ſeeing they can diſcerne nothing before them, but flames of ever-burning fire, ready to devour them, as 'tis reported of the Infants of <hi>Saguntum,</hi> (many Plagues and Judgements threatning that place) they ſtarted back into the wombs of their Mothers, as it were, abhorring to be born into ſo troubleſome a world.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. Part.</note> The time when <hi>Abraham</hi> dyed? <hi>In a good Old Age, and old Man and full of Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a good old age,</hi> 1. Naturally, being free from thoſe Aches, Fevers, and noyſome diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which are incident to old age; As 'tis ſaid of <hi>Moſes, His eye was not dim, nor his natural force abated,</hi> Deut. 34.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Morally, Not only an old Man, but <hi>a good old man;</hi> full fraught with ſo many ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous excellencies, as might denominate him good; as his years did proclaim him old.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Full of years, Annorum Satur,</hi> even facia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſatisfied with years: Having lived ſo long, that he deſired not to have his daies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed: or elſe <hi>full of yeares,</hi> that is, having fulfilled that, for which he came into the world, <hi>finiſhing his courſe with joy;</hi> and with <hi>David, ſerving his generation, before he fell aſleep,</hi> Acts 15, 36, In oppoſition to whom are <hi>months of of vanity,</hi> or empty months, <hi>Job.</hi> 7.3. when men die and leave no Teſtimony behind them, that ever they were alive, and ſo they are buried in death, <hi>Job.</hi> 27.15.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49740:8"/>
            <p>Seeing it is here recorded of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as a mercy, that he died in <hi>good old age, an old Man and full of years:</hi> We may obſerve, that old age is a bleſſing; So 'twas promiſed unto <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 15.15. <hi>Thou ſhalt goe to thy Fathers in peace,</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt be buried in a good old age,</hi> Paul glories in it, being ſuch an <hi>one as</hi> Paul <hi>the aged,</hi> Philem. 9. This is the promiſe which is annexed to the fifth Commandment, <hi>That thy daies may be long in the land.</hi> And it is part of that bleſſing, which the Lord will give to them that fear him, <hi>They ſhall ſee their childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Pſa. 128.1.6. Sure I am, the contrary is threatned as a judgement to the houſe of <hi>Eli, That an old man ſhould not be of his houſe,</hi> 1 Sa. 2.32. Bloody and cruel men are menac'd that they <hi>ſhould not live out half their time: He ſhall ſhake off his unripe grape as the Vine, and ſhall caſt of his flower as the Olive,</hi> Job. 15.33. It is obſerved, that from the beginning of the world, to ſome generations after the flood, the Son ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dyed before the Father, <hi>Haran</hi> an Idolater is firſt noted to have <hi>died before his Father Terah, in the Land of his nativity,</hi> Gen. 11.28. The experience of many ages hath alſo confirmed an other obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi> That God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Crown'd the reverend Biſhops &amp; Fathers of the Church with this bleſſing of the Patriarch <hi>Abraham,</hi> even a good old age: It is a bleſſing in a ſpecial manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe 'tis honorable, the ſame word which ſignifies honour <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may be fetched
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49740:9"/>from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>an old man, becauſe of that venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is due to old age, <hi>The hoary head is a Crown of glory,</hi> Pro. 16.31. <hi>Gray hairs are the beauty of old men,</hi> Pro. 20.29. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently reproved thoſe old men who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of their own haire, and took, <hi>Exuvias alieni capitis, forſan immundi, forſan gehennae deſtinati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grande neſas &amp; morte pian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, cum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo juvenis non aſſurrex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit. <hi>Juv.</hi>
               </note> the excrements of other men, &amp; thoſe, it may be, who have been unclean, or elſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors. The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Embaſſadors being in the <hi>Theatre</hi> at <hi>Athens;</hi> roſe in ſolemn reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence when an old man came in thither; God himſelf commands this, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.32. <hi>Thou ſhalt riſe up before the hoary head; and honour the old man, and fear thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe it brings wiſdome along with it, together with prudence &amp; experience, <hi>with the ancient is wiſdom, and in length of daies is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> Job. 12.12. This is one reaſon why the Devils are ſuch <hi>Daemons,</hi> ſuch knowing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, becauſe they are of ſo many thouſand years ſtanding, St. <hi>John</hi> ſuppoſeth, that ſuch as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in years, ſhould tranſcend others in divine underſtanding; <hi>I write unto you Fathers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye have known him that is from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.13.</p>
            <p>This concerns not children, and all younger people only, in acquainting them what reverence they ought to pay unto their Fathers, and ſuch as are ſtricken in years, <hi>deſpiſe not thy Mother when ſhe is old,</hi> Pro. 23.22. The young Stork is very obſervant of the old ones, <hi>And the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49740:9"/>of the vallies ſhall pull out his eyes that is not ſo:</hi> Their own Children ſhall plague them too, as they have been irreverent to others. Thoſe in <hi>Aelian</hi> were more than barberous, who inſtead of foſtering &amp; dutifully obſerving their old friends, they rid themſelves, of their company; and by an untimely violence, thruſt their decreped rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions out of the Land of the living.</p>
            <p>But here's ſomething for old men themſelves to ruminate upon; All mercies bring obligations a long with them: If old men would have that honour and Reverence which is due unto them from others, they muſt reverence themſelves, and maintaine their own honour? The High Prieſt might not defile himſelf, becauſe the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of God was upon him,</hi> Numb. 6.7. So neither ſhould old men do any thing that is black and ugly, leſt they ſhould ſtain their white hairs, which are the <hi>beauty of old Men.</hi> It being demanded of an old <hi>Lacedemonion,</hi> why he wore ſuch a long Beard? that I might (ſaid he) thereby be continually minded to do nothing that is diſhonourable; No ſpectacle me thinks is ſo monſtrous, and ſtrikes ſo much horror into the heart of a religious ſpectator, as to behold a drunken, ſwearing, obſcene, profane, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant old man. <hi>Lucian</hi> hath hit right, in ſtiling his body <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a living Sepulchre, or crawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grave; and I may as juſtly take the liberty to term his Soul, in the language of <hi>Auſtin, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha putredinis,</hi> a bundle of rotteneſſe, or <hi>Cage of unclean birds:</hi> Like ſome old withered thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49740:10"/>or ſuperannuated Foreſt, which harbers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Toads and Serpents: The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> old ſhooes and mouldy bread, ſome old Oake or old Raven, may deſerve as much as ſuch old men, ſuch as are not only children in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>overgrown boy's</hi> (as one calls them) <hi>with gray beards,</hi> like <hi>Rehoboam</hi> forty (nay ſixty) yeares old, yet very Children, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.7. But are drenched in the ſinck of all manner of corruptions, and, which is worſt of all, ſuch perſons are ſeldom obſerv'd to be<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, from their habituated enormities. <hi>The wicked man though he live an hundred years, ſhall be but an accurſed wretch,</hi> Iſa. 65.20. <hi>As Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is honourable in all,</hi> but 'tis when <hi>the bed is undefiled;</hi> So old age is a <hi>Diadem of glory,</hi> but 'tis, <hi>when it is found in the way of Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pro. 16.31. which leads me to another Corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from this part of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Old age is then a Compleat bleſſing, when 'tis joyned with goodneſs.</hi> In a good old age, when old men are like <hi>Maliſon, old diſciples,</hi> Act. 21.16. or like <hi>Obadiah,</hi> ſuch as have <hi>feared the Lord from their youth,</hi> 1 Kin. 18.12. Like the Almond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and the Vine, which naturaliſts obſerve to bear the beſt fruit when they are old; So if theſe bloſom and <hi>bring forth more fruit in their age,</hi> they may plead with God, as <hi>David</hi> in his extremity, <hi>Caſt me not away in old age,</hi> Pſ. 71.9. Such leave a ſweet ſavour behind them when they are gone, their memories are imbalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they need no monuments to continue their names, beſides Epetaph's ingraven upon the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49740:10"/>hearts of good men, Braſſe and Marble are but cold remembrances to theſe. The great <hi>Moloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſes,</hi> and <hi>Pyramids</hi> (which are but as ſo many deſolate place, Job 3.14.) will be eaten up with the teeth of time. The perpetual Lamps made of molten gold (the fond and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Tapers) which have been affected by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> to give light unto, or elſe to drive away evil ſpirits from their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines,</hi> ſhall ſooner be extinguiſhed then this Motto, <hi>(Of a good old Man)</hi> ſhall be blotted out.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Abraham</hi> being old and good, was ripe for death, and ready to goe to his Grave, like <hi>a ſhock of corn coming in, in his ſeaſon;</hi> Job 5.26. I muſt crave of you, that laſt act of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to goe along with me to his funeral, and that's the laſt ſtage of my text.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Part.</note> 
               <hi>Abrahams</hi> burial, <hi>He was gathered to his People:</hi> Here's no need of your Sobbs or lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ſuch Funerals (me thinks) are as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as weddings, where the parties to be interred are not only old, but good too. Tis<note n="‖" place="margin">Sedenti ad epulas lacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ingerere, importunum eſt, ne non tam amaſſe illum quam noſtra quaeſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe de illocom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur. <hi>Ber. Ser.</hi> 27. in Cant.</note> unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to mingle our cries with their Hoſanna's, unleſſe we would ſeem either to envy their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, or to love our ſelves, more than them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He was gathered to his people in his Soul, that is, unto the Saints. As Gods ſervants rejoice in the ſolemn meetings and company of ſuch as excel in vertue in this life; ſo when they die, they ſhall be gathered to the <hi>Congregation of the firſt born, and ſet down with Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49740:11"/>
               <hi>Jacob in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> The Souls of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, ſhall go to their people, to blaſphemers, unclean perſons, <hi>Gorah</hi> and his company. <hi>Judas</hi> went <hi>to his place,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael was gathered to his people,</hi> Gen. 25.17. So the Souls of holy men ſhal goe to the <hi>Souls of juſt men made perfect. He was gathered to his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though when we die, we leave many of our acquaintance and ſweet relations behind us: yet we ſhall not goe among utter ſtrangers, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our fore-fathers, brethren and friends, who have here profeſſed the Faith, and departed in the fear of Gods Holy name: Therefore, as many heathens rejoyced, that they were to goe to the Ghoſts of <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Plato:</hi> So may the ſervants of God exult upon their death-beds, that they are to be gathered unto Chriſt, the Patriarches, the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious company of the Apoſtles, and the noble Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Martyrs.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſoul was gathered to his people, then it was not as ſo much water ſpilt upon the ground, much leſs was it annihilated. That Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſprang from Hell, which tels us that the ſoul is <hi>Emanatio e craſi,</hi> or <hi>Exhalatio e Sanguine,</hi> and at laſt doth <hi>tranſire in mentem mundi, velin A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomos diſſipatur.</hi> I tremble to Engliſh it: for me, let this Philoſophy return from whence it came, I had rather tell you (which is the very truth) that the ſpirits of Gods people, being let looſe from the priſon of the body, mount upwards, and are gathered to their people.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49740:11"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Baſil. p. 128.</note> Death is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Abolition but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>only; a diſſolution of the <hi>Compoſitum,</hi> or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſoul from the body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He was gathered to his people,</hi> in reſpect of his body, in that he was buried in the cave of <hi>Macpelah,</hi> in the <hi>feild of Ephron,</hi> in the next verſe to the text, where <hi>Sarah</hi> had been buried before. The body is the Caske of a precious jewel, the temple of the Holy Ghoſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is decently to be laid up, and lodged in the Chambers of the Earth. It hath been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a curſe, either to have no burial, or the <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of an Aſſe.</hi> And as all Nations have had a care to bury their dead; So I know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ more than in the manner of their burials; the Aegyptians were very prodigal of their ſpices, in Embalming their dead, <hi>quantum redolent duo funera,</hi> Chriſt was <hi>anointed to his burial,</hi> Mat. 26.12. The <hi>Romans</hi> burn their dead, and put their aſhes in Urnes, ſome put their dead into figures of glaſſe, and ſo dryed them in the Sun, others (being more barberous) eat them up, and intombed them in their own bowels. Yet it hath been the deſire of moſt people to be buried by their Anceſtors, and to mingle their duſt with that of their friends; as if the <hi>clods f thoſe vallies</hi> (where their allies have been bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried) <hi>had been moſt ſweet, Jacob</hi> gave ſtrict or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to be buried in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Gen. 50.5. <hi>Joſeph</hi> alſo gave the ſame order concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his bones, 2.25. <hi>Ruth</hi> told <hi>Orpha, where thou dyeſt, I will die, and there will I be buried,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49740:12"/>Ruth 1.17. <hi>Eutichius,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> tells us, that <hi>Adam,</hi> with all his poſterity unto <hi>Noah,</hi> were buryed in <hi>Spelunca Alcamne,</hi> in a cave called <hi>Alcamne.</hi> Sure I am the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, by reaſon of his diſobedince was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that <hi>his Carkaſs ſhould not come into the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of his Fathers,</hi> 1 Kings 13.22.</p>
            <p>After that ancient and laudable right (which hath been accounted no ſmal priviledg in former ages) our worthy Patriot, is come to ſleep with his Fathers, and to be gathered to his people. And ſo having performed the Obſequies due unto the Father; It is time (order alſo requires the ſame) to celebrate thoſe rights which belong to the Son; A genuine Son of his Father <hi>Abraham:</hi> and well may he ſo be called, his very<note n="*" place="margin">Pureſoy. Pure Faith.</note> name im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports as much; his profeſſion and practice were ſuitable to his name, in maintaining, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending <hi>for that faith which was once delivered unto the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you ſee (according to my firſt predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) I am conducting you to another funeral, and in order thereunto, I am faln upon a new text: I muſt alſo beg your patience to hear an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sermon, only I ſhall quicken and refreſh your attentions, as that Philoſopher in <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Rhetoricks, did his weary and almoſt tyred au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, with <hi>Hem demonſtrationem!</hi> If you have any devotion left, liſten now to that which may be for your great advantage, and is worth no ſmall ſumme the learning. Many of thoſe flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which I ſhall ſtrew upon this Hearſe, you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49740:12"/>may gather into poſies for yourſelves, their <hi>ſmell ſhall be as the ſmell of Lebanon,</hi> whilſt I open a box of Spikenard, and ſhed amongſt you the oyntment of his name; your ſenſes may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be delighted, but your faces may be made to ſhine.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not mount into panegyrical flouriſhes, in the honour of the man, though his excellent vertues would worthily bear, if not exact them in the words of our own Hiſtorian concerning <hi>H.</hi> 7. But I ſhall uſe the words of ſobriety and truth. His name hath no need to be imbelliſhed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrains of Rhetorick, <hi>Nullius laudibus creſcat, nullius vituperatione minuatur,</hi> as <hi>Macrobius</hi> of <hi>Virgil:</hi> The ſtature of his fame can receive no addition of Cubites from my oratory; As it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obſcured and ſullied by any black mouthes whatſoever: for himſelf, I dare ſay, (though againſt my preſant enterprize) that I ſhould never have procured his approbation or allowance in ſteering this courſe; He had rather <hi>his own work ſhould praiſe him in the gates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 31.31.</note> than that <hi>Homer</hi> himſelf ſhould ſet forth the praiſes of him, or them; only give me leave, firſt to aſſert, and make good the way I am going, in vindicating it in the general, from the ſlanderous charge and unreaſonable imputation of ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we have not only the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for our preſidents, but the primitive Fathers, by their many Elegies, and funeral orations, have given pregnant Teſtimonies, that they never thought it unlawful, to give the dead their due.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49740:13"/>
               <hi>A Noſtrate Philoſophia non eſt alienum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ser. 26. in fratrem <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium.</hi>
               </note> It is no way repugnant to Chriſtian philoſophy, or ſound Divinity. So <hi>Naziauzen;</hi> But we have more authentick authority, yet <hi>David</hi> himſelf compiles a panegyrick in the commendation of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonat</hi> after their deaths, <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; <hi>Jonathan were ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in their lives.</hi> And again, <hi>the beauty of Iſrael was ſlain on the high places,</hi> 2. Sam. 1.19.23. The Prophet <hi>Je.</hi> 22.15.16. does the like for <hi>Joſia.</hi> He tels <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> that his Father <hi>did eate and drink &amp; do judgement and juſtice, he judged the cauſe of the poor and needy:</hi> No fear then of ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>The firſt Topick to be ſpoken too, is the birth and extraction of this lamented Genleman, both which were very Noble, and ancient: by the help of ſome Records (which I have ſeen) I could lay before you a glorious Scheme of a numerous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degree; I could lead you many generations back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (if not to the conqueſt it ſelf) and all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long point at the Eminency of his illuſtrious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors: But I muſt leave this taske to better Heraulds and Hiſtorians than my ſelf. If you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe <hi>Eſcutchions,</hi> you may be your own Heralds: Had not ſome inhumane, &amp; Scrilegious perſons (like ſo many <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi>) defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſome monuments in this place, you need not have gone far to have ſeen what I ſay; The loſſe is ſo much the leſſe in that 'tis repair'd, and his Geneology in ſeveral branches of it, redeemed from injurious time, by the dexterous and happy pen of <hi>a living</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">By the Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, <hi>Robert</hi> the now Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>library,</hi> who voluntarily tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him in his life time, an accurrate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49740:13"/>portraiture of the ſame; beſides,<note place="margin">Note that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven of his anceſtors were, ſlain at the battle in <hi>Boſworth feild,</hi> in aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the right of <hi>H.</hi> 7. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the or cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el uſurper. <hi>R.</hi> 3.</note> the gallantry of his family cannot be forgotten in this place, ſo long as <hi>Boſworth</hi> is ſo neer; I ſay it again, The gallantry of his family ſhall not be forgotten; ſo long as <hi>Boſworth feild</hi> hath a name in ſtory, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have his forefathers <hi>been men of renown only</hi> for greatneſs and valour, but famous too in the <hi>Congregation,</hi> for truth in Religion: And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he out-went his <hi>Father Abraham;</hi> for his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Terah ſerved other Gods,</hi> Joſhua 24.2. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did he degenerate from them, which made him the more to be honoured by good men. As I have had alwaies an high eſteem of the <hi>Ancient Fathers and Writers</hi> of the Church: So I have accounted, that there is a tribute of reverence &amp; reſpect to be given to ancient families in the State; eſpecially ſuch (like the <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſome<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tamerlande</hi> did ſo, when he was about to ingage with his enemies, to the intent his courage might be rouſed up.</note> others) who often read over the Noble Acts of their Anceſtors, than they might be inflamed to do the like: Such as do not ſtain that honour they have received, but rather tranſmit it to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with advantage; Therefore the word which is tranſlated <hi>Nobles</hi> ſignifies <hi>white ones,</hi> Jer. 27.20. to ſhew, that ſuch as are <hi>brought up in Scarlet, ſhould not imbrace dung-hills,</hi> and defile their garments in the mity puddles of any dirty and ignoble practice. This <hi>Worthy</hi> was a <hi>white one</hi> indeed, for though there was an orient luſtre in his birth, yet his new birth did out-ſhine and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle the glory of that, <hi>virtuibus quam natalibus vel tantis nobilior:</hi> His vertues were a better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament unto him, than his cout of Armes. The
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49740:14"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nomen pietatis quam poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, <hi>Tertul.</hi>
               </note> name of piety was more ſweet, than that of a Gentleman, as <hi>Theodoſius</hi> gloried more that he was a Chriſtian, than that he was an Emperour that was beſt in his account which did rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to make him good than great.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Anton. lib. 8.</note> As the <hi>leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> (that is, of glory,) is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the greateſt of the Sons of men upon Earth; ſo the loweſt degree of ſaving grace, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the higheſt excellencies of <hi>Stock</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> Theſe are poor low &amp; beggarly trappings, empty husks, glorious bubbles, as they are deſtitute of <hi>goodneſs and Truth in the inward parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we ſhall take the dimenſions of his worth the better if we conſider him in his general ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, Moral, Politick, and Divine; As a <hi>Man</hi> a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In his moral capacity, <hi>as a Man:</hi> and here I an amide ſuch a throng of perſonal excellencies that I know not to which to turn firſt, ſhould I rehearſe them all, the remainder of your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would utterly be exhauſted, ſhould I paſſe them all by in ſilence, I ſhould wrong both his worth and your expectations &amp; if I ſhould ſpeak of this or that, without taking notice of the reſt, this would be (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> of <hi>Agricola) injuria virtutuns,</hi> a wrong to his other vertues, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this triple-horned <hi>dilemma,</hi> I ſhall like a traveller, caſt a tranſient eie upon thoſe magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent ſtructures where I muſt not dwell, Who knew him that did not alſo know his exemplary temperance, His very heart roſe againſt debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery in others, and if at any time he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49740:14"/>into the company of intemperate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, his delight was no more than a Marriner takes in his ſhipwrack, or a poor ſlave in his gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Juſt ſo he was not only, no ſwearer, but <hi>fieared an oath,</hi> Eccle. 9.2. His veracity, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity in words and promiſe, were no leſſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable: He accounted it the greateſt reproach to boggle or falſifie in either.</p>
            <p>How curteous and affable to all? <hi>quot verba, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> aromata:</hi> His words were even perfumed with lenity and condeſcention to men of the meaneſt rank. So far as he could without making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf cheap, and expoſing his authority to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, <hi>ex ore ejus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 23.</note> 
               <hi>non tam verba quam mell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fluxiſſe videantur,</hi> in the words of <hi>Vincentius.</hi> he ſpake roſes, and hony dropped from his lips: or in the words of a better author; <hi>In his lips were the Law of Kindneſſe,</hi> Prov. 31.26. I have gone as high as I can, yet I am narrow and ſhort in expreſſions, <hi>revocetur ab orcis—Tullius.</hi> Here's work for another <hi>Cicero.</hi> neither was he of the number of them who ſalute, complement, and ſet a garland of fragrant words about one's head, yet all that while aim at the <hi>fifth rib,</hi> that ſo innocent and credulous men may fall a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to their diſſimulation. He firſt of all acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me with a court-like Aphoriſme, out of a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <note n="*" place="margin">Written by Henry <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> Manuſcript by him; but it was with no ſmall dislike. It was this, many are <hi>omnibus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigni, paucis familiaris, nullis emici; Kind to all familiar with few, but true friends to none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might ad de much concerning his judgement
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49740:15"/>and underſtanding in ſeveral ingeuous and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtudies, as Hiſtory, Herauldry; but above all, in that art of all Arts, <hi>Divinity;</hi> of his well regulated Charity, alwaies making a judicious choice of the objects upon whom he beſtowed it. But I ſhall conſider him,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his pollitical capacity; and herein, firſt, as a ſubject of this Kingdom, and hence I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto you for a pattern worth your immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, his peaceable diſpoſition and ſubmiſſion to lawful authority; <hi>Obedience and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are the ſignes of an honeſt Man,</hi> ſaid he<note n="‖" place="margin">Ki. <hi>James</hi> in his ſpeech at the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at <hi>Hampton-Court.</hi>
               </note> that ſpake like an Oracle. When <hi>Bellona</hi> firſt beat up her unhappy Drums, and ſpread abroad her bloody ſtreamers, he ſo far abhorred thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, that he procured a licence of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, of happy memory, to travel beyond the Seas. And when the Seas were as tempeſtuous as the Land, he choſe rather to bury himſelf live, in a private and obſcure concealment of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; (as<note n="*" place="margin">Ah, potius bello patiaris in iſto; te <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> putet eſſe ſuam. <hi>Lucan.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pompey</hi> once reſolved to do in a tender compaſſion of <hi>Rome</hi>) rather then behold, much leſſe joine his hand in the rending the bowels of his own Country; When a little before his death ſome were telling the animoſities, and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents that were abroad, (as we are all too apt to be <hi>Athenians in ſick mens Chambers,</hi> though we now injoy thoſe mercies, which not long ſince we could not hope for, unleſſe from his hand who hath beſtowed them, and would have thought them cheap, though purchaſed with a torrent of blood) he plainly told me, that the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49740:15"/>anger of male-contents aroſe from the leven of their own ambition; angry they were, but it was with (with <hi>Agrippina</hi>) becauſe they did not reign themſelves. Many dying men, (as <hi>Jacob</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) have had prophetick ſpirits, and ſo had he: As Naturaliſts have obſerved, that ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Talpae mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituri aperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt oculos.</note> creatures ſee cleareſt, when about to die; when I told him, that it was us;ual with way ward men, if they have not every <hi>punctilio</hi> they deſire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, (like ſo many children) they are unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for what they have. He gave an <hi>Adaequate</hi> and full conſent thereunto, as comprehending his own ſenſe; And ſince I am faln upon this ſubject I call to mind what a<note n="‖" place="margin">Mr. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington.</hi>
               </note> Prophet of your own, I mean a Miniſter of the next adjoyning pariſh, hath left upon record. <hi>'Tis irkeſome</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for wild birds to be cooped in a cage of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and order, or to be ſtrait lared, after they have gone looſe ſo long;</hi> I wiſh, we were not wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a commentary upon that Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As a Magiſtrate, ſo he was an ornament of that order. <hi>He put on Righteouſneſs, and that ploathed him, Judgement that was a Robe and a Diadem,</hi> Job. 29.14. <hi>Eyes to the blind, Feet to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Juſtice is ſelf ſet forth to the life, <hi>Juſtice animated;</hi> his grave &amp; regular life was enough to put ſin out of countenance,<note place="margin">Vira cenſura pulns imderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> and the intimation of his pleaſure; his nod had the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a command. Ready he was, (whilſt he had his health) to execute the lawes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in puniſhing ſcandalous offenders, and relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch as were oppreſſed. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49740:16"/>have them to be Rulers over his Cattle, <hi>who were men of activity.</hi> Gen. 47.6. Much move ought they to be active who are Rulers over men: Hear this ye great one, draw forth that ſword which God hath in ruſted to you, <hi>to the terror of evill works and workers;</hi> but remember to be (like God himſelf) <hi>a Sun and a ſhield</hi> to the poor and perſeouted. If any one of you ſhall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holſter prophaneſſe, either by your power or example: I may juſtly Alarum you in the words of <hi>Zach.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Howl O ye Oaks of Baſhan,</hi> great men are called Oaks in Scripture, as men in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral are often compared to trees. If you, like Oaks, ſhal bring forth Acorns for hogs; that is, favours for wicked men; <hi>Then howl O ye Oaks of Baſhan.</hi> This was the reaſon that the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Heads of the people to be hung up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord againſt the Sun,</hi> Numb. 25.4. And that at the end of the world, <hi>the Kings of the Earth, the great men, &amp; mighty men ſhal hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Dens and rooks of the mountains, and ſay to the mountains and rocks, fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth upon the Throne,</hi> Rev. 6, 15.10. Becauſe all theſe had abuſed their power, and as <hi>Lucifer</hi> falling from Heaven drew the third part of the Stars after him: So theſe have corrupted others by their example, therefore their judgement ſhall be the more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His Divine Capacity,<note place="margin">Moralia cum ſide, ſunt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina: &amp; divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſine ſide, ſunt moralia.</note> as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> though his former excellencies, both moral and civil, were both divine and ſpiritual in him, as they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49740:16"/>were acted by the ſtrength of Grace, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the glory of God, yet that which we call Religion in a more immediate ſenſe was his greateſt delight; and thoſe that were Godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and truly Religious, were higheſt in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, <hi>Et ſcias eos vertutibus abundare, &amp;c.</hi> we may ſafety conclude that thoſe men have a great ſtock of vertue in themſelves,<note place="margin">Plinie epiſt.</note> who ſet their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon vertue in other men: <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the brethren,</hi> 1 John 3.14. Neither was his Religion of any novel date; All the Locuſts of old new furbuſhed hereſies and Schiſms (which have ſwarmed out of the bottomleſſe pit in theſe later times) could never faſten upon him, to blaſt and deface the verdure of his more ancient and Catholick profeſſion, but <hi>ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſweet breath of pure truth in the Church of God.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bp.</hi> Morton.</note> He was none of thoſe, who having <hi>drunk old wine ſtrait-way deſired Now,</hi> Luke 5.39. Or rejecting the old<note n="‖" place="margin">Apoſtolicae doctrinae man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na revomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus haertieae novitatis ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Mamna</hi> of found doctrine, longing for the <hi>Muſhrom inventions of brain-ſick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which ſprang up but the other night: And that he might be aſſiſted in his domeſtick, and more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick devotions in his family (which were daily as frequent as his moals) He borrowid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from the Altar, by commonly keeping in his houſe a Chaplain in orders, and he his abſence, that the duty might neither beneglected nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan'd, by raſh evaporations and daring effuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He had a form of prayer read conſtanily twice a day in his family &amp;c. So diligent was he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49740:17"/>in hearing the word, that when through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſſe he could neither go diſſtand; yet we had his preſence at ſermon; untill at laſt I thought he would have breathed his laſt, whilſt I had been preaching. A good Emperour ſhould die in the feild, a good Miniſter in the Pulpit; and it ſeems. A good Chriſtian could willingly expire in the Congregation.</p>
            <p>Indeed he was ſo far from running forth into heats about Religion, eſpecially about ſhuffers and philacteries, and other circumſtances of low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er moment, (as if theſe ſhould rather be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his obedience, than diſputes, that eyen in other matters he was obſerved to expreſſe more Religion in his practice, than in his words; like deep wavers that make the leaſt, noiſe, and hot like the <hi>Indian</hi> figtree, whoſe leaves are as broad as a targer, but its fruit no bigger than a bean. This reſervednes might eaſily ſuggeſt unto ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers an occaſion of ſuſpition, that his heart did ſcarce abound with goodneſſe, ſeeing his mouth was no forwarder to ſet it forth. But when he was in private. O how have I been affected to hear him give a large teſtimony of his faith when we have been mingling experiences, &amp; bringing forth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evidences for Heaven, how have I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulted to hear him relating the way and method he had walked in, How he and his former <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> did conſtanly <hi>take ſweet counſel together,</hi> by entring, into their cloſet (beſides family ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes) and praying jointly unto Almighty God, there in <hi>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Happy couple! ſo to live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49740:17"/>in this world, that they might live together to all eternity. Beſides this act of devotion, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night before he took his reſt, he ſat him down in his own ſtuddy, there he paſs'd a ſevere ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie upon himſelf, examining and calling to the teſt, the ſeveral actions of the day, and wherein he had miſcarried; thereto abhor himſelf, and implore the pardon of his Heavenly Father, in cancelling that debt. <hi>His account ſhall be leſſe at the great day of recompences, that often thus ſincerely and impartially reckons with himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he was conſcionable in giving to God the things that were Gods: So he had a ſweet return from God, as of many other bleſſings, ſo of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aſſiſtance and ſupport, in time of his extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that he might reſemble his Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and his deliverance upon the <hi>Mount,</hi> when God had taken from him by a lamentable ſtroke, his dear ſpouſe, <hi>the joy of his heart,</hi> and <hi>delight of his eyes,</hi> when his Children were diſpers'd with the tempeſt of Warr, his eſtate rent and torne, and he himſelf penſive, at theſe rugged tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of divine providence; He took his Bible in his hand, and ſo his ſpirit was calmed, as it were from Heaven, in reading, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 31. 1, 2, 3. <hi>In thee O Lord do I put my truſt, let me never be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, deliver me in thy righteouſneſſe. Bow down thine eare to me ſpeedily, be thou my ſtrong Rock, for an houſe of defence to ſave me; for thou art my Rock and my Fortreſſe, therefore for thy names ſake lead me and guide me:</hi> And may not he juſtly be called <hi>the Son of Abraham,</hi> who
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49740:18"/>could thus live upon prayer and promiſes, and by faith evaded and conquered the greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties.</p>
            <p>We ſhall confront this Father and Son (with their due diſtances) in a cloſer parallel, and draw to a concluſion. Was <hi>Abraham</hi> an indulgent huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? So was he.<note n="*" place="margin">We look for the effect of thoſe prayers in his ſurvive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off-ſpring. Sure children of ſo many prayers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcarry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as is ſaid of <hi>Auſtin</hi> in reſpect of his Mother <hi>Monica.</hi>
               </note> Was he a praying father for his children; <hi>O that Iſhmael might live before thee?</hi> So was he. Was <hi>Abraham</hi> tried and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with Croſſes and afflictions? So was he. Was <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of a numerous ſeed according to the ſpirit? ſo was he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh: A ſeed, the branches where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are tranſplanted into ſeveral Countries (like a conſtellation of ſtars, broken up and ſet in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct orbs,) where they are the <hi>heads of their Tribes.</hi> Did <hi>Abraham command his houſhold after him?</hi> So did he; never did child reſemble his father more in any bodily Symmetry and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, than he did <hi>Abraham</hi> in this particular; like another <hi>Antoninus,</hi> he oft viſited his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ejecting ſuch perſons as were prophane and ſcandalous, as ſo much Froth and Scum, with <hi>David a wicked perſon would he not know,</hi> Pſ. 101. 6, 7. <hi>Zim and O chim, with Satyres and other unclean birds, were not ſuffered to dance there,</hi> Iſa. 13.21, 22. This was a reddy way to bring a bleſſing upon his own affaires, and to convince the vileſt ſervants of their Errors, to the intent they might repent and reform: That <hi>ſo their ſpirits might be</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Quorum non zelas ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem ſubice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem nimis ambitioſe ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicas. <hi>Ber. Ser.</hi> 23. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had <hi>Abraham</hi> his failings and [infirmities?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49740:18"/>witneſs his cowardiſe in <hi>Gerar,</hi> Gen. 20.2. So (that you may not ſay I have made an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Saint of him) had he alſo; yet I muſt do him ſo much right, that when I laid before him his impatiency &amp; fretting, to which he had been prone; with humility he acknowledged his fault, but withall aſcribing the praiſe to the grace of God. He told me, that he bad much mortified, wea kned, and conquered that once domineering paſſion.</p>
            <p>But to keep to the text, <hi>Abraham</hi> was great, and rich; yet <hi>he gave up the Ghoſt,</hi> willingly ſubmitting himſelf to the ſtroke of death. So had this his Son a very large eſtate, a beautiful and pleaſant<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Wadley</hi> has a commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſite; a wholſom and delicious aires it is a rich and pleaſam Seat. <hi>Burton. p.</hi> 259.</note> habitation, All other comforts whereon wordlings ſet their hearts; yet he had ſo far ſtudied the nature of them all, that he had found them to be only <hi>bracteata felicitas,</hi> nothing but as a little gilded Copper, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet his Heart no more upon them, than on ſo many fleeting, empty, and miſerable comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; this he ſignified to me, when I ſpake my feares unto him, <hi>vizi.</hi> That the great things of the world do clogg and retard our motions towards heaven, and ſtake us down ſo faſt unto the Earth, that we are unwilling to dye, ready to preſer a palace in <hi>Paris,</hi> before Paradice it ſelf. His reſolution and anſwer was like that of<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Anton.</note> 
               <hi>Antoninus,</hi> no more to be in love with any thing below, than within ſparrow flying over his head, which perhaps he might never ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. He had alſo ſtudied the charter of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joyes, when he cry'd out of his paines. I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49740:19"/>told him, that in Heaven, no malladies ſhould attatch him, there all tears ſhould be wipt from his eyes: True in deed, ſaid he, there I ſhall have reſt, and not till I ſhall come thither. And can he chuſe but give up the Ghoſt willingly, who meditates aright upon the vanity of this world, and the bleſſings of that which is to come; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was obſerved towards his latter end, to be as earneſt to have his Coach and Horſes to be prepared to bring him to this place of his burial, as ever the was to goe a progreſſe of pleaſure, looking for the meſſenger of death; as <hi>Jacob</hi> did for thoſe Charriots, which ſhould carry him to his Son <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He dyed in a good old Age.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caeſar etſi glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria celum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimus ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſibi ſatis vix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit non ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſatio. Reip. quae praeſidio care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non poſſit ipſius &amp; tutela. <hi>Sleid.</hi> Wiſ. 4.9.</note> It was obſerved of him, <hi>that he was an old man at twenty,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of us, his Allies, the Church and whole Kingdome, ſo his death was immature; but in reſpect of himſelf, ſo he was a <hi>good old man, for wiſdome is the gray hair to men, and an unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted life, is old age.</hi> In this ſenſe it is that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> is called a <hi>good old man,</hi> for his age; was far inferiour to many that liv'd before him, <hi>but an hundred threeſcore and fifteen yeares</hi> in the <hi>v.</hi> before the Text, yet he is ſaid firſt of any to be <hi>an old man, and full of years,</hi> becauſe his, many vertues did crown his age, in making it the more awful; and<note n="*" place="margin">Invida quem Lacheſis rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum rtiete ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de nova. Dum numerat palmas credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit eſſe ſevem <hi>Mart. li.</hi> 10. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 58.</note> illuſtrious.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is brought hither to be <hi>gathered to his people, and to ſleep with his Fathers,</hi> untill the day of reſurrection, that as he injoyed many of <hi>Abrahams</hi> mercies in his life, ſo he might be like
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49740:19"/>him in his death too, that (like <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi>) <hi>in death they might not be divided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heitherto I have been converſing with the dead, and tracing the footſteps of two Heroick Ghoſts. Now a word or two at parting, to you that are yet alive, that ſo I may end as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To all in general, give me leave to make ſuch a dole amongſt you, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his auditors, after he had made an oration upon the life of <hi>Athanaſius, Vertutes illius inter vos partiamini,</hi> now fall a dividing his vertues amongſt your ſelves: But be ſure that every one take ſome. This will be a better badge of being at a funeral, than either Roſemary or Ribbons; when you are diſmiſs'd, goe alſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with your ſelves, who may be the ſubject of the next funeral, and ſay with the Apoſtles, <hi>Maſter, is it I? Maſter, is it I?</hi> Only let me prompt you to ſo much humanity, as to take your leaves of this our Reverend Father, before you goe; ſpeak to him in the words of <hi>Luther</hi> to his dying daughter, <hi>Ingredere in cubile tuum cum pace,</hi> good night dear friend, farewell, fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, goe to thy bed of reſt, draw thy curtains, ſhut thy doors about thee; <hi>Et nos mox aderimus,</hi> It ſhall not be long, ere we ſhall all come unto thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a ſpecial and peculiar manner, to you that are the children, and that, both by way of Conſolation and direction.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49740:20"/>
            <p n="1">1. By way of conſolation, <hi>vos chara capita, vos chara pignora,</hi> you that were the ſweet pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his love; <hi>The branches, which once ſate about his table,</hi> and ſprang out of this ſtem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.<note n="*" place="margin">Finis vitae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus nobis luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuofus amicis triſtis. Tacitus de Agric.</note> I confeſs the thoughts of his death are very ſad: He is <hi>Commune</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Bernardus de Gerardo.</note> 
               <hi>damnuns,</hi> a common loſſe unto us all, but eſpecially unto you his neareſt allies; yet the<note n="*" place="margin">Majore ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum damno quam ſuo. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. de <hi>Tito.</hi>
               </note> loſſe is more yours and ours, than his, <hi>ne defleatis igitur;</hi> Therefore weep not for him, who ſhall never weep more. What though you have loſt a tender Father? yet you have cauſe to<note n="‖" place="margin">Non dolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quod pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem amiſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſed laetan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum potius quod talem habueritis <hi>Ambro.</hi> de fratre <hi>Satyro.</hi>
               </note> rejoyce, that you had ſuch an one to looſe. Loſt did I ſay? Nay, he's perfected in an advantagious change of his ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Look beyond death, and think with your ſelves, as if you ſaw him cloathed with<note n="*" place="margin">Non tam mortem cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate quam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitatem. <hi>Cyp. Epiſt.</hi> 82.</note> immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. What though he be faln aſleep, into an Iron<note n="‖" place="margin">Ferreus ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſomnus Virg.</note> ſleep, nay, a ſleep of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Hom.</note> Braſſe? yet he ſhall certainly wake again. <hi>Cur impatienter feratis ſubductum,</hi> in the words of <hi>Tertullian;</hi> Why ſhould you grieve that he is gon aſide, <hi>quem cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditis reverſurum,</hi> who you believe to return again, never to leave you, never to die any more? He ſhall get by the grave, that ſhall be as fullers earth, and Nitre to purg him from all corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible qualities: And ere long he ſhall break forth out of thoſe clods, as<note n="*" place="margin">Cum dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mientem au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divimus, evigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la: tutum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> as the Sun from ſome cloud that had eclipſed and obſcured it, or as the <hi>Phenix</hi> ſprings more vigorous and active out of her own aſhes.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t phoenix ruptis pullulat exuviis.</q>
            <p>By way of Direction, I ſhall not betray my ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49740:20"/>ſo far as to ask you this queſtion, did you love your Father? For you may anſwer me in the words of <hi>Peter, Thou knoweſt that we love him:</hi> And me thinks I hear you ſay, good reaſon we had to do ſo, <hi>omnis in Aſcanio,</hi> all his love was upon us; wel, love him ſtill, love his memory, follow his advice and counſel, in fearing the God of your Fathers, and loving each other; remember the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> Jer. 35.5. Having pots of wine ſet before them, ſaid, <hi>We will drink no wine, for</hi> Jonadab <hi>the ſon of</hi> Recab <hi>our Father commanded, ſaying, ye ſhall drink no wine,</hi> goe ye and do likewiſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all that ſavory and fartherly counſel which he hath imparted unto you; O let not that die with him. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Antoninus, Hoc Solo patriae, quod genuit nocuit,</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in only he prejudic'd his Country, in that he left ſeed, a <hi>Commodus</hi> behind him. But as 'tis your honour to have had ſuch a Father, ſo let your carriage be an honour to his memory: That as it is ſaid of <hi>Rich.</hi> the firſt,<note n="‖" place="margin">Sol occubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it nox nulia ſequuta eſt.</note> ſucceeding his Father <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, ſo it may be ſaid of you: <hi>Though the *Sun be ſet</hi> in his weſtern bed, yet by reaſon of your luſtre, we may be free'd from the ſhadows of a darkſom night. So ſhine then, in your ſeveral ſphears here, as members of the Church and State, That you may ſhine as ſo many Stars in the Firmament of glory hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
